Finding aid for the Friends of the Los Angeles River records, 1987-2013 LSC.2215
UCLA Library Special Collections
Friends of the Los Angeles River records
1930-2014
1983-2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Friends of the Los Angeles River
LSC.2215
68 linear feet (145 boxes, 1 record carton, 2 shoeboxes, 8 flat boxes, 1 map folder)
The Friends of the Los Angeles River (FoLAR) is a non-profit, urban environmental organization, founded in 1986 and focused on saving, restoring, and reviving the Los Angeles River. FoLAR--with a board of directors, a technical advisory board, and a program that encompasses education, community organization, and political action--has advocated for an integrated 52-mile greenway and has stressed the need to address the 30 different governmental agencies that has each had some jurisdiction over the river. FoLAR records include documentation of activities that focus on protecting and restoring the natural and historic heritage of the Los Angeles River and its riparian habitat through inclusive planning, education, and wise stewardship. Included in the collection are correspondence, administrative records, research materials, photographs, maps, files relating to the various activities of the organization, including publications, advocacy and fundraising events, political and legal action, and publicity.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
RESTRICTED ACCESS: Use of audio and moving image material requires production of listening and viewing copies.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lewis MacAdams, 2013.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9975416473606533
Biography/History
The Friends of the Los Angeles River (FoLAR) is a non-profit, urban environmental organization, founded in 1986, that is focused on saving, restoring, and reviving the Los Angeles River. The Los Angeles River is 52 miles long, extending from Canoga Park in the northwest section of the San Fernando Valley to San Pedro Bay, the site of the Port of Long Beach and the adjoining Port of Los Angeles. The Los Angeles River drains most of the Santa Susanna, Santa Monica, and San Gabriel Mountains. FoLAR--with a board of directors, a technical advisory board, and a program that encompasses education, community organization, and political action--has advocated for an integrated 52-mile greenway and has stressed the need to address the 30 different governmental agencies that has each had some jurisdiction over the river.
FoLAR founded in 1986 by Lewis MacAdams, Pat Patterson, Roger Wong. Early board members include:
Lewis MacAdams, founder and long-time president of FoLAR, as well as poet, performance artist, author, screenwriter, documentary filmmaker, and journalist. MacAdams has been an activist since the 1960s, when he lived in Bolinas, California, and was the youngest member of the Bolinas water board district.
Tom Janeway, attorney
Denis Schure, a designer, whitewater canoeing expert, and Los Angeles River safety instructor
Jim Danza, environmentalist and expert in water resources and water quality, who headed FoLAR's Technical Advisory Board. This board is comprised of engineers, biologists, and planners, and has the mission of investigating the means of revitalizing the Los Angeles River system as a natural resource through science and education
Sara Rose, who was, at the time, working in the film industry
Martin Schlageter, environmentalist and conservationist
The City of Los Angeles was founded along the Los Angeles River in 1777. Until the completion of the Los Angeles Aqueduct in 1913, the river was the primary source of water for the City of Los Angeles. Catastrophic floods of 1934 and 1938 precipitated the concrete channelization of the Los Angeles River by the United States Army Corps of Engineers, a major infrastructural project that spanned over 20 years and transformed the River into a single-purpose storm water drainage and flood-control channel. At one point, there were 17,000 workers paving the river by hand, constituting an important jobs creation program during the waning years of the Great Depression.
The whole drainage area of the Los Angeles Basin and its surrounding mountains had been reengineered to serve the urban growth of Los Angeles. As a result of the construction of the aqueducts--providing a reliable water source for Los Angeles, the channelization of the river, and the elimination and taming of its many small tributaries--the process of urbanization accelerated. This efficient, single-purposed system for carrying away storm water runoff meant that ground water was no longer being replenished. Even during times of prolonged drought, Los Angeles can experience tremendous amounts of rainfall over short periods of time without being able to capture any of the water for its own future use. Following its successful channelization and due to the efficiency of its function as a flood-control system, the Los Angeles River received toxins and trash that was flushed into the river from adjoining neighborhoods.
The Los Angeles River with its sole function as a flood control channel to whisk storm water runoff to San Pedro Bay as quickly and efficiently as possible, became a worldwide symbol of the negative impacts that urbanization has on the natural environment. With the fewest acres of parks per capita in the United States, Los Angeles and its river was the poster child for failed environmental stewardship. The river was known for its graffiti, its homeless encampments, and as the site of several Hollywood movies. A perceptual shift began in 1985 when the newly constructed Donald C. Tillman Water Reclamation Plant began to discharge water from its Van Nuys site in the San Fernando Valley. The plant was designed to treat 40 million gallons of wastewater per day, the Los Angeles River began to take on the appearance of a year-round river with flourishing populations of birds, fish, and crayfish.
Floods in 1992 made clear that the river's ability to function as a flood-control system would need to be enhanced and expanded as the city grew. FoLAR, along with Heal the Bay and TreePeople, filed a lawsuit in 1995 to halt the execution of a proposal by the Los Angeles County Department of Public Works and Army Corps of Engineers to raise the walls along the river. The lawsuit was unsuccessful but was an opportunity to articulate an alternative strategy of watershed management. FoLAR advocated for a watershed approach to flood protection, allowing more space for the river to flood during heavy storms. This approach would correct the inadequate size of the channel, constructed in 1938 and failing to accurately estimate the huge growth in the urban area of Los Angeles. FoLAR's watershed approach included acquiring abandoned waterfront factories and rail yards along the river. This involved working with organizations, such as The Trust for Public Land, the California State Coastal Conservancy, and the Santa Monica Mountains Conservancy, to identify and work toward the acquisition of appropriate parcels along the entire length of the river.
Friends of the Los Angeles River has been involved in several projects and studies alongside other groups and individuals, including:
The Chinatown Yards Alliance, which was a coalition of environmental, community, and civil rights groups, comprised of FoLAR, the Natural Resources Defense Council, the Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Society of Los Angeles, Concerned Citizens of South Central Los Angeles, and the Northeast Renaissance Corporation, with the goal to turn the Chinatown Yards/Cornfield into a public park. Arthur Golding, University of Southern California Professor of Architecture & Planning, joined FoLAR with designs to turn the Cornfield into a public park with a school and housing
A coalition for a state park at Taylor Yard, for which Golding had a hand in developing a park development plan similar to the Chinatown Yards/Cornfield project
The Los Angeles River Master Plan Study, conducted by the Los Angeles Country Department of Public Works
Water Quality and Beneficial Use Study of the River, an engineering feasibility study of turning the closed railroad yard into a multi-purpose flood-retention basin and park
Multiple Use and Flood Control study at Taylor Railroad Yard, in collaboration with the California Department of Water Resources and the Los Angeles County Department of Public Works
An investigation into alternative urban flood control technologies and systems
The United States Army Corps of Engineers Water Supply and Conservation Reconnaissance Study
The City of Los Angeles River Task Force demonstration project in the San Fernando Valley
And the Los Angeles County Museum of Natural History's biological inventory of the river.
FoLAR's educational activities have included River Watch, a volunteer water-quality-monitoring program to measure and control water pollution. Its advocacy activities have included city and countywide task forces for river restoration. FoLAR was instrumental in the creation of the Los Angeles and San Gabriel River Watershed Council, now known as the Council for Watershed Health. Political supporters have included Los Angeles mayors Tom Bradley and Antonio Villaraigosa; state senators Art Torres, Tom Hayden, and David Roberti; Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors member Gloria Molina; and Los Angeles City Councilmembers Ed Reyes, Eric Garcetti, and Tom LaBonge.
FoLAR has initiated and joined in several lawsuits regarding the Los Angeles River, some of which are listed below.
A lawsuit related to the Chinatown Yards/Cornfield site, which ceased to be used as a rail yard in the late 1990s. The city recruited Majestic Realty, the largest owner and developer of commercial space in Los Angeles County, to propose an industrial development for the zoned-industrial site. Majestic's proposal was supported by Richard Riordan, then mayor of Los Angeles, and former Councilmember Mike Hernandez and encompassed the development of buildings totaling 909,200 square feet of light manufacturing and warehouse. FoLAR opposed this plan, as its vision for the site was for a central park with both active and passive recreation.
Another suit revolved around the former rail yard known as Taylor Yard, also zoned industrial. This 165-acre site included 40 acres of remediated land, ready for development. The developer, Lennar Properties, proposed industrial space complemented by retail and a movie theater, use that appealed to the surrounding Cypress Park, Glassell Park and Mount Washington. However, FoLAR's vision was for a 165-acre river park with multiple functions, including flood prevention, habitat restoration, and active recreational use on the 40 remediated acres.
In 2001, California State Parks purchased the two former industrial rail yards, Chinatown Yards/Cornfield and Taylor Yard, marking the end of a successful battle against developers and others who wanted to construct warehouses on the site, and leading the way for a new approach to land use along the river and downtown.
Friends of the Los Angeles River continues to pursue its founding mission of advocacy for the Los Angeles River through education, collaboration and imagination. Among its stated goals are the restoration of the river's natural habitat through the application of flood-protection technologies that include reforesting and re-vegetating the river's watershed to control seasonal flooding and debris flow; encouraging the use of reclaimed water for irrigation and recharge of aquifers in order to promote sustainable development; the creation of bikeways, pedestrian paths, and horse trails on the riverbanks; promoting recreational use of the river, such as canoeing and kayaking; placing the Los Angeles River bridge on the National Historic Registry; and, in collaboration with other groups and agencies, activities such as community-based river clean-ups, graffiti removal, educational programs, and water monitoring.
Scope and Content
Friends of the Los Angeles River (FoLAR) records consist of the records of the non-profit organization. Included in the collection are correspondence, administrative records, research materials, photographs, maps, files relating to the various activities of the organization, including publications, advocacy and fundraising events, political and legal action, and publicity.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in four series:
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1987-2012
Series 2: Research Materials, 1941-2014
Series 3: Legal Records, 1990-2011
Series 4: Activity Files, circa 1930-2013
- Series 1: Administrative Records, 1987-2012
  Scope and Content
  This series contains mission statements and strategic plans, along with meeting agendas and minutes from FoLAR's Board of Directors and Technical Advisory Board. Other organizational documents include administrative files, grant guidelines and applications, and correspondence. This series is also comprised of commendations received by FoLAR, documents concerning the organization of volunteers for various activities, and promotional material.
  Organization and Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Arts and Cultural Events, 2005-2008 (Box 112, Folder 5)
  - Blank Stationary, undated (Box 112, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors: Bios, undated (Box 94, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1987-1992 (Box 94, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors: Development, 1989-2007 (Box 94, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors: Executive Director Reports, 1993-1994 (Box 94, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 1989-1991 (Box 91, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 1992 (Box 91, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 1993 (Box 91, Folder 3-4)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 1994 (Box 91, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 1995-1999 (Box 92, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2000-2001 (Box 92, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2002 (Box 92, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2003 (Box 92, Folder 4-5)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2004 (Box 92, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2004 (Box 93, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2005 (Box 93, Folder 2-3)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2006 (Box 93, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2007 (Box 93, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2008-2009 (Box 94, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2010 (Box 94, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2011 (Box 94, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors: Meetings, 2012 (Box 94, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors: Miscellaneous, 2000-2011 (Box 94, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors: Retreat, 2006 (Box 94, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors: Rosters, 2000-2004 (Box 94, Folder 6)
  - CEIP Funds, 1990-1991 (Box 108, Folder 3)
  - Contacts: Call Registers, 2002 (Box 110, Folder 3)
  - Contacts: Contact Lists, 1990s-2000s (Box 110, Folder 1-2)
  - Contacts: Database, 2004 (Box 110, Folder 4)
  - Contacts: Los Angeles Unified School, 1998 (Box 112, Folder 7)
  - Contacts: Photos, undated (Box 110, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1990-2012 (Box 117, Folder 3-4)
  - Donors: Clean-up Potential Sponsor Letters, 2000 (Box 97, Folder 5)
  - Donors: Corporate, 2000s (Box 96, Folder 4-5)
  - Donors: Donor Acknowledgements, 2004 (Box 97, Folder 1-2)
  - Donors: Donor/Member Acknowledgements, 2005 (Box 97, Folder 3-4)
  - Donors: Metropolitan Water District, 2003-2007 (Box 96, Folder 1)
  - Donors: Nonprofits and Foundations, 2000s (Box 95, Folder 5)
  - Donors: Political, 2000s (Box 96, Folder 2)
  - Donors: Potential Donor Letters, 2001-2003 (Box 95, Folder 4)
  - Donors: Private, 2000s (Box 96, Folder 3)
  - Donors: Sponsor Acknowledgements, 2003 (Box 96, Folder 6)
  - Fiesta/Awards Dinner, 2001-2002 (Box 116, Folder 1)
  - Fiesta/Awards Dinner, 2003 (Box 116, Folder 2)
  - Fiesta/Awards Dinner, 2004 (Box 116, Folder 3-5)
  - Fiesta/Awards Dinner, 2005-2006 (Box 117, Folder 1)
  - Fiesta/Awards Dinner, 2007-2010 (Box 117, Folder 2)
  - FoLAR Commendations, 1993-2010 (Box 112, Folder 9)
  - FoLAR Commendations, 1995-2012 (Box 158, Folder 9)
  - FoLAR contributions to others, 2000s (Box 95, Folder 2)
  - Fundraising, 1990s (Box 104, Folder 1)
  - Fundraising, 2000s (Box 104, Folder 2)
  - Fundraising, 2000 (Box 105, Folder 1)
  - Grants, 1990-2011 (Box 107, Folder 6-8)
  - Grants: Altria Grant Proposal, 2007 (Box 106, Folder 12)
  - Grants: Annenberg Foundation, 2005-2007 (Box 106, Folder 2)
  - Grants: Capital Group Grant, 2005 (Box 106, Folder 11)
  - Grants: Contracts, 1990-2011 (Box 107, Folder 5)
  - Grants: County and City of Los Angeles Grants, 2000s (Box 105, Folder 7)
  - Grants: Daimler-Chrysler Grant, 2006 (Box 105, Folder 6)
  - Grants: David Bohnett Foundation, 2006 (Box 106, Folder 10)
  - Grants: Education Grants, 1995-2007 (Box 107, Folder 9)
  - Grants: Getty Internship Program, 2007 (Box 106, Folder 3)
  - Grants: Grant Guidelines, 1990-2005 (Box 108, Folder 1)
  - Grants: Grant History at FoLAR, 1993-2003 (Box 105, Folder 5)
  - Grants: Grant Proposals, 2000s (Box 105, Folder 4)
  - Grants: J.R. Haynes and D. Haynes Foundation, 2008-2009 (Box 107, Folder 1)
  - Grants: KPCC Underwriting Info, 2002 (Box 108, Folder 2)
  - Grants: Liberty Hill Foundation, 2001-2005 (Box 106, Folder 4)
  - Grants: Los Angeles City Disbursement of Funds, 2006 (Box 105, Folder 12)
  - Grants: Los Angeles County Disbursement Forms, 2006-2007 (Box 106, Folder 1)
  - Grants: Los Angeles Turf Club Grant, 2003 (Box 105, Folder 8)
  - Grants: Luckman Gallery Urban Design Exhibit, 2000 (Box 107, Folder 3)
  - Grants: Parsons Foundation, 2009 (Box 106, Folder 5)
  - Grants: Patagonia Environmental Grants, 2003 (Box 106, Folder 13)
  - Grants: Potential Funding Sources, 2003-2009 (Box 105, Folder 2)
  - Grants: Potential Funding Sources, 1994-2004 (Box 105, Folder 3)
  - Grants: Resources Legacy Fund, 2005-2006 (Box 105, Folder 10)
  - Grants: Rivers and Mountains Conservancy Grant, 2008 (Box 106, Folder 6)
  - Grants: Rose Foundation, 2000-2004 (Box 106, Folder 7)
  - Grants: Rose Hills Foundation, 2009 (Box 106, Folder 8)
  - Grants: Santa Monica Mountains Conservancy Grant, 1993 (Box 107, Folder 4)
  - Grants: Taproot Foundation, 2009 (Box 106, Folder 9)
  - Grants: Urban Streams Restoration Program, 1990-2008 (Box 107, Folder 2)
  - Grants: Will J. Reid Foundation, 2002-2003 (Box 105, Folder 9)
  - Grants: Zell Family Foundation, 2003 (Box 105, Folder 11)
  - L.A. River Clean Up, 1990s-2000s (Box 98, Folder 1-4)
  - L.A. River Theatrical Trailer, 2007 (Box 112, Folder 4)
  - L.A. River Tours, 2006 (Box 112, Folder 3)
  - Meeting notes: Handwritten, 2004-2006 (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - Membership, 1990-2011 (Box 109, Folder 4-5)
  - Mission Statements, 1990-2011 (Box 110, Folder 7)
  - Office Records, 1990s-2000s (Box 108, Folder 4-5)
  - Office Records: Facility Use Agreements, 2006-2008 (Box 108, Folder 8)
  - Office Records: FoLAR Library, undated (Box 108, Folder 6)
  - Office Records: Getty Intern, 2008 (Box 108, Folder 10)
  - Office Records: Los Angeles River Center, 1995-2008 (Box 108, Folder 7)
  - Office Records: Permits, 2000s (Box 108, Folder 9)
  - Office Records: Personnel, 1990s-2000s (Box 109, Folder 1-3)
  - Promotional Material, 1992-2009 (Box 113, Folder 1-4)
  - River School, 2003-2011 (Box 112, Folder 6)
  - Riverwatch: Coastal Conservancy Grant, 2000-2004 (Box 114, Folder 4)
  - Riverwatch: Grants, 2000-2005 (Box 114, Folder 5)
  - Riverwatch: Grants, 2000-2005 (Box 115, Folder 1)
  - Riverwatch: Insurance and Permits, 2003-2005 (Box 114, Folder 2)
  - Riverwatch: Personnel, 1998-2005 (Box 114, Folder 3)
  - Riverwatch: Records, 2000-2005 (Box 115, Folder 2-4)
  - Riverwatch: Volunteers, 2003-2004 (Box 114, Folder 1)
  - RioFest, 2008 (Box 115, Folder 5)
  - Sponsorship Rejections, 2002 (Box 95, Folder 3)
  - Strategic Plans, 1998-2011 (Box 111, Folder 1-3)
  - Technical Advisory Board, undated (Box 111, Folder 4)
  - Technical Advisory Board, 1991 (Box 111, Folder 5)
  - Technical Advisory Board, 1992 (Box 111, Folder 6-7)
  - Technical Advisory Board, 1993-1994 (Box 112, Folder 1)
  - Technical Advisory Board, 1995-1999 (Box 112, Folder 2)
  - Volunteers, 2000s (Box 113, Folder 5)
  - Volunteers: Water Quality Monitoring (Misc.), 2003-2004 (Box 113, Folder 6)
  - Website, 2003-2010 (Box 110, Folder 6)
- Series 2: Research Materials, 1941-2014
  This series contains reports, newsletters, photographs, maps, and press clippings from other environmental advocacy organizations, as well as governmental sources, utilized by FoLAR for research purposes.
  This series is primarily arranged alphabetically by subject. Press clippings are further arranged by year.
  - AEG Sustainability, 2012 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Aerial Photos, undated (Box 47, Folder 7-8)
  - Aerial and Street Level Photos, 1980s (Box 47, Folder 2-3)
  - Air Pollution, 2001 (Box 57, Folder 8)
  - Algalita Foundation Plastic to Plankton, 2001 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Architect/Landscape Drawings, 2006 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - America Outdoors, 1997-1998 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Arundo, 1990-2001 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Bicycle Paths in Los Angeles, 1997-1998 (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Biota of Los Angeles River (Plants), 1989-2010 (Box 39, Folder 9)
  - Biota of Los Angeles River (Fish), 1989-2008 (Box 39, Folder 10)
  - Biota of Los Angeles River (Birds), 1990-2011 (Box 39, Folder 11)
  - Blake Gumprecht, 2001-2010 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - Book: California Wildlife Conservation Challenges, 2007 (Box 153)
  - Book: Fragile Ecologies: Contemporary Artists' Interpretations and Solutions, 1992 (Box 153)
  - Book: Master Plan for the Lower Arroyo Seco, 1988 (Box 153)
  - Book: Moule and Polyzoides, by Elizabeth Moule and Stefanos Polyzoides, 2006 (Box 153)
  - Book: Not a Cornfield: History/Site/Document, 2007 (Box 153)
  - Book: Rio Porciuncula, 1990 (Box 153)
  - Book: River of Words: Images and Poetry in Praise of Water, edited by Pamela Michael, 2003 (Box 153)
  - Book: Texas Environmental Almanac, 1995 (Box 153)
  - Book: Verses from the Poet to the River of Los Angeles Porciuncula (2 copies), 2000 (Box 153)
  - Book: Voyageur... to the San Fernando Valley, 1964 (Box 153)
  - Book: Watersheds of the Mind, by Giuseppe Moretti, 2005 (Box 153)
  - California Guide to Environmental Literacy, 2004 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - California State Coastal Conservancy, 1994 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Channel Clearing, 1997 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Cleanup/Recycling, 2001-2002 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Coastal Cleanup, 1993 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Community Enhancement Plans, 2000-2003 (Box 159, Folder 1)
  - Conferences, 1988-2011 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Conferences, 2004-2005 (Box 90, Folder 4)
  - Conservancies, 1986-2010 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Cultural Activities and Proposals, 1986-2013 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Dams, 1948 (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Debris Basin Management, 1989-1998 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Department of Water and Power, 2008-2011 (Box 89, Folder 1)
  - Dredging- Los Angeles River, 1998 (Box 88, Folder 4)
  - Economic Development, 1992-2014 (Box 40, Folder 8-9)
  - Elected Official Training Academy, 2004 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Environmental Advocacy Publications, 1997-2013 (Box 49, Folder 3-4)
  - Environmental Education, 1994-2001 (Box 60, Folder 3-5)
  - Environmental Justice, 1998-2007 (Box 49, Folder 5-6)
  - Environmental Organizations, 1996-2005 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Environmental Protection Agency, 1990 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Protection Agency, 2002-2011 (Box 60, Folder 7)
  - Event Announcements, 2011-2012 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - FEMA, 1992-1996 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Filming Permits/Los Angeles River, undated (Box 41, Folder 2)